NYSUT Vice-President's Office, Maria Neira Files. 6174/016
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- National Association of Latino Elected and Appointed Officials (NALEO) DC Summit 10/13/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  Draft agenda for summit, the State of Latino Education; summary of National Council of State Legislatures (NCSL) final report on No Child Left Behind; recommendations of NCSL task force; presentation sheets on NCLB for NYS NAACP workshop; report, Immigration Trends and Their Implications for U.S. Schools, Migration Policy Institute; AFT presentation sheets re NCLB
- NALEO National Education Leadership Initiative (NELI) National Advisory Committee, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  Letter to Maria Neira from NALEO, thanking her for agreeing to serve on advisory committee of NELI, January 5, 2005; invitation to join and description of NELI, October 18, 2004
- National Board for Professional Teaching Standards, 2005-2007 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  Letter to Maria Neira from Johanna Duncan-Poitier, deputy commissioner of education, re districts receiving Mentor Teacher Internship Program (MTIP) funds, July 14, 2005; Education Week article, "Sidetracking the Debate On Teacher Quality," November 15, 2005, with cover letter to Board of Directors of National Board for Professional Teaching Standards (NBPTS), December 14, 2006; NBPTS biographies of slate of candidates for Exceptional Needs Standards Committee, with cover letter to Board of Directors, November 20, 2006; NYSUT charts, National Board Certified Teacher Data as of January 9, 2007; Education Week online article, "National Board Teachers No Better Than Other Educators, Long-Awaited Study Finds," May 9, 2006; NBPTS bylaws, list of board members, and other materials, sent to Maria Neira as new board member, November 9, 2006
- National Board for Professional Teaching Standards Meeting 12/8/06, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  NYSUT Information Bulletin re National Board Certification, February 2006; Q&A for NYSUT Local Leaders; paper, "Using National Standards to Redesign Master's Degrees for Teachers: A Guide for Institutions of Higher Learning" by Joan Packer Isenberg, February 2003; brochures; presentation sheets re statistics on certification, funding; list of certified teachers in NYS; CD, "Awareness and Recruitment Toolkit," December 2006
- National Board for Professional Teaching Standards Certification 2005-2007 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  A Candidate's Guide to National Board Certification, 2006-2007 and 2005; letter from Maria Neira congratulating teacher for certification, with tentative agenda for celebration event, March 2005; proposal for summit meeting; fact sheet on certification rates; list of candidates (?); map of 2004 National Board Certified Teachers by school district locations
- National Board for Professional Teaching Standards Press Conference 12/2/04, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  NBPTS Press release, "Students of National Board Certified Teacher Achieve Larger Gains on Statewide Math Test in Florida; New Research Points to National a Board Certification as Key Indicator of Teacher Quality," November 17, 2004; NYSUT press release with attached list of NYS teachers earning national certification, December 2, 2004; related memos
- National Board for Professional Teaching Standards Press Conference 11/30/05, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  Press conference agenda, November 30, 2005; talking points for Maria Neira for National Board Certified Teachers Press Conference; text of remarks by Neira; memo with additional information as context for Neira; national data re certified teachers; list of certified teachers
- National Board for Professional Teaching Standards National Board Certified Teachers, 2005-2007 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  Key points about the 2006 NBPTS score release, noting dramatic increase; press release, "Number of National Board Certified Teachers Tops 55.000: Nearly 7,800 teachers achieve National Board Certification in 2006," January 9, 2007; 2006 NBPTS Score Release Key Messages and Talking Points; talking points for Maria Neira at May 21, 2005, press conference; presentation sheets for NBPTS Board of Directors meeting, "National Board Certified Teachers: Rhetoric, Research, and Reality," October 14, 2006; Education Week article, "Sidetracking the Debate on Teacher Quality: Have high expectations given way to the lowest common denominator?" re shift in emphasis since of No Child Left Behind; press release, "NBPTS Elects New Board Members: Board members include 11 National Certified Teachers," November 14, 2006
- National Center for Missing and Exploited Children, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Description of nonprofit organization and services
- NEA Staff Meet and Greet 11/30/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Invitation and memos
- NYSUT Employees Outreach Network (NEON) Committee 9/9/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Memo from NEON Committee re year-end results and 2005-2006 planned activities; report of activities and charities benefitting from Dress Down Day, June August 2005; materials re Guide Dog Foundation for the Blind, Catholic Charities, March of Dimes, American Cancer Society, other charitable organizations; memos re events
- NEON: Special Events Day 4/29/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Letters to community charity organizations from NEON Committee, and copies of contribution checks
- NEON Committee, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Agenda for September 22 meeting; minutes of September 9 meeting; holiday gift wrapping service/fundraiser flyer and signup sheet; year-end report and 2005-06 schedule; list of Title I schools in need of improvement under No Child Left Behind, for NYC and upstate, September 2002; correspondence re NEON activities for March-May 2005, December 2004-February 2005; materials re Dress Down Day
- New Local Presidents Conference July 11-14, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Conference program; bullet points, Maria's intro for Jim Wood (final and earlier draft); outline of general remarks by Maria Neira; intro to AFT History Video: "A Proud Tradition," NLPC, July 12; agenda
- New Local Presidents Conference (NLPC) Debriefing 10/6/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Evaluation forms
- New Local Presidents Conference (NLCP) Meeting 7/1/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Conference program; related correspondence
- NYS AFL-CIO, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Constitution of New York State AFL-CIO, as amended through August 2004; letter from NYS AFL-CIO president Denis Hughes to Maria Neira, congratulating her on her election as vice president of the state federation, September 12, 2005; cover memo to Executive Council members re federal election law for union staff using union resources, with attached document, January 2006
- NYS AFL-CIO Executive Council Meeting 12/09/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Meeting agenda; resolution re executive structure; resolution re retirement of Paul Cole as secretary-treasurer; letter of resignation from Cole, November 3, 2005; minutes of August 3, 2005, meeting; budget projection, by department, for period of July 1, 2005 to June 30, 2006; letter to Maria Neira informing her that she had been recommended for election as vice president of the New York State AFL-CIO, October 31, 2005; Neira biographical sketch; list of program services recommended for Retiree Services; Unity Caucus 2005 membership list (directors); letter to NYS AFL-CIO president Denis Hughes from Rep. Vito Fosella, informing him that Worker's Compensation funding of $125 million for 9/11 recovery workers had been restored, November 29, 2005
- NYS AFL-CIO COPE (Committee on Political Education) Report 2005 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Letter from House Speaker Dennis Hastert to Rep. Vito Fosella, assuring him that $125 million in Worker's Compensation funding for 9/11 recovery workers would be restored, November 21, 2005; newspaper clipping from The Chief Civil Service Leader: The Civil Employees' Weekly, re restoration of funding, December 2, 2005; COPE Report, calling field operation for Budget Reform proposal one of the worst statewide efforts in recent history, in contrast to the winning campaign for the Transportation Bond Act, December 9, 2005; campaign materials for propositions and candidate; unofficial Board of Elections results for propositions, by county
- NYS AFL-CIO COPE Day at the Races 16th Annual Benefit 8/4/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Invitation to benefit for Committee on Political Education (COPE) at Saratoga Race Course
- National AFL-CIO Convention 7/25-29/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  AFL-CIO Convention Key Issues for AFT Delegates, noting AFT position on resolutions; letter from Westchester-Putnam Counties AFL-CIO Central Labor Body to Maria Neira, asking that NYSUT pay one-time extra month in dues to AFL-CIO so that delegates would be assured of ability to vote at convention, August 1, 2005; critical report of July 4, 2005, NEA convention, by the Education Intelligence Agency, forwarded to NYSUT officers, July 5, 2005; e-mail reports of NYSUT at AFL-CIO convention, July 24-28, 2005; update from AFT Legislation Department, "House Narrowly Approves CAFTA After Midnight Vote," July 28, 2005; AFT press release, "Statement by Edward J. McElroy, President, American Federation of Teachers, on CAFTA (Central American Free Trade Agreement): Wrong Rx for U.S. Economy and Workers," July 28, 2005
- NYS AFL-CIO 1/5/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Invitation to State of the State Breakfast Reception
- NYS Council of School Superintendents September 25-27, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  Conference program: "Achievement and the Arts: Advancing Student Success"; letters of invitation to Charles Santelli and Maria Neira
- NYS Math League, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  Memos requesting check for winner of 2005 Mathematics League Competition, address correction; copy of check; correspondence re 2004 winner; memo ordering plaque, specifying wording; correspondence re 2003 and 2002 winners
- New York Teacher 9/5/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  New York Teacher story list; NEA wraparound for NEA members, to accompany first mailing of New York Teacher, post-merger, September 7, 2006
- New York Teacher Meeting 2/15/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  New York Teacher story list
- New York Teacher 10/3/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  New York Teacher story list; halftone photos with captions. See also Kadamus
- New York Teacher Meeting 9/19/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- New York Teacher 8/22/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  New York Teacher story list; production schedule; schedule of Communications Planning meetings
- New York Teacher 6/14/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- New York Teacher: Standards 6/9/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- New York Teacher 5/23/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  New York Teacher story list; memos
- New York Teacher 5/9/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  New York Teacher story list; memos re meetings
- New York Teacher 4/25/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  New York Teacher story list; article from Wall Street Journal, "Reading, 'Riting, Reform," 4/7/05, with note to Maria Neira's attention; partial AFT executive vice president report (via e-mail)
- New York Teacher 3/28/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- New York Teacher 2/28/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- New York Teacher 2/14/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- New York Teacher 1/28/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- New York Teacher 1/18/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  New York Teacher story list; article, "Governor's Budget Proposal Better Than Expected"; proposed officer visit schedule, 2004-2006
- New York Teacher Meetings, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  List of Communications meetings for the remainder of New York Teacher publishing year
- New York Teacher Meeting 11/15/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  New York Teacher story list; memos re unification talks
- New York Teacher Meeting 11/1/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- New York Teacher Meeting 10/18/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- New York Teacher Meeting 10/4/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- New York Teacher Meeting 4/5/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- New York Teacher / Communications Meeting 5/17/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 38)
- New York Teacher / Communications Meeting 5/3/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- New York Teacher / Communications Meeting 4/19/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- New York Teacher / Communications Meeting 3/8/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- New York Teacher / Communications Meeting 2/9/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- New York Teacher / Communications Meeting 1/26/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- New York Teacher Communications Brainstorming Day 6/11/04, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  Agenda for Communications Brainstorming Day; handwritten notes; memo re meeting
- No Child Left Behind (NCLB) 2004 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  Letter from the NYS Education Department to U.S. Department of Education with formal submission of revised Accountability Workbook reflecting NYS's approved plan to calculate Adequate Yearly Progress under No Child Left Behind, and formal amendment to workbook for calculating progress of students with significant cognitive disabilities, August 21, 2004; "Failing Our Children" summary report by FairTest: The National Center for Fair and Open Testing, critiquing No Child Left Behind, May 2004; "Accountability Left Behind: While Children and Schools Face High Stakes Testing, Tutoring Companies Get a Free Ride," a study by the Association of Community Organization for Reform Now (ACORN) and the American Institute for Social Justice; list of schools failing to meet AYP under No Child Left Behind, September 20, 2004; State Education Department field memos. See also AFT No Child Left Behind; see also Committee of Practitioners
- NCLB National Conference of State Legislatures (NCSL), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  Letter to NYSUT executive vice president Antonia Cortese from the president of Nassau BOCES Central Council of Teachers, Local 2551, noting that the National Council of State Legislatures issued a report that No Child Left Behind was a flawed, convoluted, unconstitutional education initiative that had usurped state and local control of public schools, and asking why the law had not been challenged in court and what action the AFT might take, March 16, 2005
- NCLB Mathematics and Science Partnership Grant Program, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  State Education Department list of awarded partnerships, 2004-2007. See also under Mathematics
- NCLB Rochester Tutoring, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  Text of article from American Teacher, "Rochester to Provide Local Tutoring," May/June 2004
- NYSUT Annual Reports, 1987-1990 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  Annual reports for 1987, 1988, and 1990
- NYSUT / NEA Membership Map, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  Map of NYSUT Election Districts, with list of school districts and affiliations (NYSUT, NEA, or both), cover memo, December 1, 2005
- Officers Advisory Committee Meeting 11/17/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  Agenda; draft (not yet submitted) New York State Center for (Independent) State Testing Reviews (STR), submitted by Westchester Institute for Humans Services Research, Inc., to Gov. George Pataki, 11/3/05; NYSUT Regents' Report Card re November 2004 Board of Regents meeting; Member Benefits Chairperson Report by Ivan Tiger
- Officers Advisory Committee Meeting Education and Learning Trust 6/22/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  Materials for new course proposed by Ro Rosen of the NYSUT Education and Learning Trust, "A Framework for Leadership," with cover letter to Chuck Santelli, June 16, 2005; course outline and syllabus; presentation sheets for NYSUT Education and Learning Trust; 2005-2006 budget proposal overview; agenda of Education and Learning Trust Board of Directors meeting, June 22; minutes of March 1 meeting
- Officers Advisory Committee Meeting 6/6/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  Memo re management/confidential salary adjustments for 2005-2006; lists of individual salaries, 2004-06 to 2007-08; full employment and salary histories of several individuals since hire
- Officers Advisory Committee Meeting 6/1/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  NYSUT 2005-06 Budget
- Officers Advisory Committee 4/12/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Officers Advisory Committee Meetings 2005 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  Schedule of meeting dates for 2005
- Officers Advisory Committee Meeting 7/22/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  Packet of resolutions referred for implementation by the Representative Assembly, with cover letter, July 22
- Officers Cabinet Retreat June 4-5, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  Officers' Retreat agenda, June 4-5; Cabinet Retreat agenda, June 5; agenda for NYSUT Local Action Project 2007 Summer Planning Conference Agenda, July 16-20, 2007; draft agenda for NYSUT New Local Presidents Conference, June 26-29, 2007; text of oral report of first vice president Maria Neira to NYSUT Executive Committee, June 7; confidential results from Equal Employment Opportunity Commission Report re racial and gender breakdown of full-time and other regular staff, 1999-2006; report re declining membership of AAUP (American Association of University Professions); dress code policy; list of NEA and/or AFT meetings/conferences, September 2006-August 2007; handwritten notes
- Officers Meeting 5/8/07, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  Agenda; May 2007 issue of Latino New York, monthly magazine of the Capital Region; VOTE/COPE 2006 Report, showing charts, graphs, and lists by regional office; management/confidential salary adjustments for FY 2007-08; memo to NYSUT president Dick Ianuzzi re resolutions to come before the AFT Exec Council meeting, May 7; list of regional office staffing; memos requesting new positions or extraordinary salary increases. See also Board of Directors meetings
- Officers Meeting 3/27/07, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  Agenda; list, NYSUT Leadership Class of 2007; tax info for NYSUT locals; booklet, NYSUT Dues Proposal 2007-08 and 2008-09 Questions and Answers; standing rules for NYSUT delegation, 2007 NEA Representative Assembly; proposed officer visit schedule; flood relief accounting as of March 20, 2007; memo re appointment of legislative representative, salary, March 26
- Officers Meeting 3/12/07, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  Agenda; Executive Committee agenda for March 16 meeting; NYSUT booklet, Guide to Program Services; AFL-CIO Executive Council Statement, "End Our Military Involvement in Iraq," March 7, 2007; confidential memo requesting increase in staffing of Travel & Conference Services, February 27
- Officers Meeting 2/21/07, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  Agenda; letter to Maria Neira from New York Immigration Coalition requesting sponsorship of Builders of New York awards celebration, February 2; materials re 2006 contribution to coalition; memo re reclassification of position, February 8; materials re NEA Representative Assembly
- Officers Meeting 2/6/07, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  Agenda; Executive Committee agenda for February 9; Board of Directors meeting agenda for February 9- 10; memo re 2007 community service award winners
- Officers Meeting 1/16/07, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  Agenda; Executive Committee agenda for February 9; Board of Directors meeting agenda for February 9- 10; memo re fundraising campaign for Martin Luther King, Jr., memorial; memo re 2007 Representative Assembly move from printing to web publication, invited speakers
- Officers Meeting Dues Discussion 1/8/07, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  Memo confirming meeting
- Officers Meeting 8/7/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  Agenda; Executive Committee agenda for August 9; Board of Directors meeting agenda for August 9; memo re NYSUT Solidarity Grant, June 20; program for NYSUT Local Presidents' Conference, August 6-8, 2006; 2006-2007 proposed governance calendar (list of meetings), updated August 1, 2006; list of NYSUT attendees at 2006 AFL-CIO COPE Convention; presentation sheets re NYSUT Research & Educational Services, presented at Local Presidents' Conference, August 2006; memo alert re training for Violent and Disruptive Incident reporting (VADIR), July 20
- Officers Meeting 6/20/06 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  Agenda; notes for opening session of staff training conference of June 19; related memos
- Officers Retreat June 14-15, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  Agenda; memo
- Officers Meeting 6/6/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  Agenda; memo re opposition to rural power line proposal; memo re deletion of term "English immersion" from proposed resolution
- Officers Meeting 5/24/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  Agenda; Executive Committee agenda for June 8; Board of Directors meeting agenda for June 26; NYSUT 2006-2007 budget: revenue and expense narrative; application for regional staff director for the Southern Tier, with attached resume; list of possible resolutions for submission to the 2006 AFT Convention, from the 2005 and 2006 Representative Assemblies
- Officers Meeting 5/9/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  Agenda; officer compensation comparison with other unions; New York Post editorial re relationship between NYSUT and financial services firm ING
- Officers Meeting 4/18/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  Agenda; New York Times clipping re "taxpayer revolt" movement stopping school budgets, April 16; proposed Administrative Professionals Day mailing lists
- Officers Meeting 4/7/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  Agenda; Professional Issues Forum on Health Care program, sponsored by NYSUT Health Care Professionals Council, April 1; memos re management/confidential promotion recommendation from general counsel's office, April 4; 2006 Leadership Institute applicants; proposed Leadership Institute Class of 2006; letter from NYSUT Civil & Human Rights Committee to NYS Teachers Retirement System, urging gradual divestment in Wal-Mart, March 15; list of state retirement systems invested in companies active in Sudan; list of priority consensus statements from March 8 Administrative Committee meeting, March 21
- Officers Meeting 3/8/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  Agenda; timeline, Communications Response to Governor's Backdoor Voucher Scheme (as of March 8, 2006); list of 2006 conferences; list of guests at 2006 Representative Assembly; urgent memo from NYSUT president Ianuzzi to Nassau presidents re need to respond immediately to tuition tax credit proposal, March 8
- Officers Meeting 2/14/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  Agenda; Executive Committee meeting agenda for February 16; draft guidelines for summer internships, February 14, 2006; Associate Press article, "Tax credits for private school parents pressed," February 14; draft letter with handwritten edits, to producers of ABC television show 20/20, demanding an on-air apology by John Stossel for his January 13 segment, "Stupid in America," which criticized teachers "who strive against enormous adds [sic]"
- Officers Meeting 1/17/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  Agenda; draft Officers' Advisory Committee meeting agenda, January 19; draft NYSUT Bargaining Units Retreat Agenda, February 15; press release, "NYSUT: Governor Turns Back on Seniors, Students and Middle Class," January 17; text of governor's budget address, January 17; draft letter to Education Commission Mills from NYS Educational Conference Board; legislative newsletter
- Officers Meeting 1/10/06, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  Schedule for management/confidential salary proposals, 2006; salary histories for several individuals
- Officers Meeting 11/15/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  Agenda; Update to NYSUT Officers on Unification Planning and Implementation, November 9, 2005; Update on Unification Planning and Implementation, October 28, 2005; letter to Kathleen Lyons, NEA-NY Executive Director, from Pauline Kinsella, NYSUT Executive Director, re unification, October 25, 2005; memos re scope of work for various capital projects; handwritten notes
- Officers Meeting 11/1/05, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 79)